<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SolidWorks on Alexander Weir</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/solidworks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in SolidWorks on Alexander Weir</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 08:02:28 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/solidworks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A New Approach to Top-Down Modeling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-down-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 08:02:28 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-down-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve all been there - one dimension change, one edited mate, and your whole SolidWorks assembly comes crashing down in a wave of red error messages, broken mates, and failed rebuild blings. Anyone who works with large assemblies has to deal with this frequently. As well as you may think you know your assembly, you will inevitably forget about a mate or other constraint somewhere that prevents you from changing exactly the dimension you need to change. SolidWorks doesn&amp;rsquo;t help you a lot with this; the dozens of broken mates that will often result from a change like that do not do a great job of pointing towards the actual root of the problem, the one mate that the over-constraint comes from.&#xA;The solution, as various websites and LLMs will point you to, is top-down modeling: a structured approach where each part is defined based on references to a single &amp;ldquo;skeleton&amp;rdquo; part that contains sketches and dimensions for your entire assembly. The promise is simple; every dimension change, every stretch or shrink or movement, seamlessly updates all associated parts to the appropriate sizes since they&amp;rsquo;re all referencing the same part. In practice, however, modeling top-down ends up creating more problems than it solves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
