<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alexander Weir</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Alexander Weir</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 08:02:28 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A New Approach to Top-Down Modeling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-down-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 08:02:28 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-down-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NOTE: While this post mostly talks about SolidWorks, the issues here are fundamental to parametric modeling and will apply to Fusion, FreeCAD, OnShape, or whatever other parametric modeling software you may be using.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve all been there - one dimension change, one edited mate, and your whole SolidWorks assembly comes crashing down in a wave of red error messages, broken mates, and failed rebuild sounds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyone who works with large assemblies has to deal with this frequently. As well as you may think you know your assembly, you will inevitably forget about a mate or other constraint somewhere that prevents you from changing the dimension you need to change. SolidWorks doesn&amp;rsquo;t help you a lot with this; the dozens of broken mates that will often result from a change like that do not do a great job of pointing towards the actual root of the problem, the one mate that the over-constraint comes from.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/me.jpg&#34;  class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;width:300px; height:300px; border-radius:10px&#34;  /&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hello! I&amp;rsquo;m Alex Weir, a Liberty University student graduating in 2028 with a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s in Computer Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I love tech, engineering, and physics and have particular skills in computer networking, having studied it for a number of years now. I have a considerable and growing collection of certifications to demonstrate my broad range of IT, networking, and security knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also on the Liberty University Collegiate Cyber Defense Competition (CCDC) team, focusing on Linux and network enumeration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projects, etc</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m studying and working on a number of projects all of the time. If you have any insights into these, let me know! I&amp;rsquo;m particularly interested in computer, electrical, and mechanical engineering topics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;completed-projects&#34;&gt;Completed Projects&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Linux from Scratch (LFS)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was an excellent learning experience. Building a Linux system from the ground up gave me huge appreciation for how much work individual distributions put into dealing with the quirks of every single package that make up a Linux system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
